<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="42"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[FLAMES

















                                                  FREEDOM MOVEMENT IN KERALA

                                                 يناطيربلا رامعتسلاا دض  رابيلم ءاملع فقوم


                                                       ಪ್ಲಾ ಸ್ಸಿ ಗೆ ಒಂದು ಕಣ್ಣು .....

                                                   ഖിലാഫത്ത് പ്രസ്ഥാനം

                                                    ബംഗാൾ വിഭജനം ഒരു


                                                               മുത്തശ്ശി നയം



















                                                                ةعبارلا ةنجللا]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[FREEDOM MOVEMENT IN KERALA


                                                                   -HAFIZ JUBAIR VARAM




                       Kerala has the unique role in independence movement being a
        region where patriotic Indians revolted against the British rulers even before the

        first freedom struggle of 1857, which was labelled by the British as ‘Sepoy
        Mutiny’. In the three zones of Kerala,which known as Malabar, Cochin and

        Travancore, many revolts took place against the British in the end of 18th

        century and in the beginning of 19th century. In Malabar,  native prince, Kerala
        Varma, Pazhassi Raja who led the revolt, while in Cochin it was leadered by

        Paliath Achan, the Prime Minister of Cochin State and in Travancore by

        Veluthampy Dalava, the Prime Minister of the State. All these revolts were
        totally suppressed by the British. Towards the close of the 19th C National

        movement was spreading in India. Many prominent persons worked for Indian

        National Congress from Kerala. G.P. Pillai, Sir. C. Sankaran Nair and Rairu
        Nambiar deserve mention. C. Sankaran Nair of Ottapalam was the first Malayali

        who president over the congress sessions. By 1919 Congress activities gained

        momentum in Malabar. Gandhiji’s influence was increasing. Non co-operation
        and Khilafat movement and Salt Satyagraha increased the national spirit in

        Malabar. Some of the early leaders were K. Kelappan, Muhamed Abdurahiman,
        K.P. Kesava Menon, and K. Madhavan Nair. In 1922 the students protested

        against the fee hike in educational institutions. This soon became a rallying

        point for pro-home rule agitation. But it was the Khilafat Movement that really
        focussed the issue more forcefully. Hindus and Muslims stood as one against

        the British and the Landlords in the Malabar region. Severe police action

        followed. But the movement lost its bearing when it finally took on communal
        overtones when armed Muslims targeted Hindus. This then became a simple

        law and order problem and the British gained complete supremacy by mercyless
        deployment of police, notably the Malabar Special Police, which to this day is a

        feared symbol of colonial oppression.The Independence movement at the

        National level had a direct bearing on Kerala’s political landscape too. The Salt




                     FLAMES
        Independent Day Special                                                                            Page 2]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Satyagraha found its echo here. The Vaikom temple entry Satyagraha for

        permitting lower castes entry into the temple gained the recognition as a direct
        challenge to the existing political and hierarchical supremacy of the rulers and

        by extension the British rule.

        By the end of 19th century, people of Kerala began to take interest in the affairs

        of the country as they felt a new hope of liberation, with the advent of the

        Indian National Congress in 1885. The earliest leader of the organisation from
        Kerala was G.P. Pilla who had initiated agitations for civil rights in Travancore

        State. A forceful writer and orator, he had wide contacts in India and Great

        Britain and became General Secretary of the Indian National Congress twice.
        Gandhiji who was then emerging as a leader, had acknowledged the help and

        guidance given to him by G.P. Pillai in the South African Indian issue and also in

        the Temperance Movement (Prohibition). C. Sankaran Nair, the noted jurist,
        was another person from Kerala who adorned the leadership of the nationalist

        organisation. Sankaran Nair has the distinction of being the only Keralite to
        become the president of the INC during its long history spanning over a century.


        In 1921, while trying to address a banned public meeting in Madras K.

        Madhavan Nair, U. Gopala Menon, Ponmadath Moideen Koya, Kurur
        Neelkantan Namboothiripad and Moothedath Narayanan Menon were arrested

        and sentenced to six months imprisonment. In the same year in April, people all

        over Malabar, Cochin, Travancore assembled on a common platform and held
        the first All Kerala Political Conference at Ottapalam under the presidency of

        Andhra Kesari T. Prakasam.

        Vaikom Satyagraha


        Historic Vaikom Satyagraha, which attracted all India attention was started on

        March 30, 1924. The Satyagraha was started to establish the right for all people
        to walk through the temple roads. Leaders like K.P. Kesava Menon and T.K.

        Madhavan led the agitation.


        Savarna Jatha’ proceeded to Trivandrum and presented a mass petition to the
        Regent Maharani of  Travancore requesting her to remove ban and give

        freedom to all people to walk through the Vaikom temple roads and to put an

        end to the practice of untouchability in the State. Gandhiji held discussions with


                     FLAMES
        Independent Day Special                                                                            Page 3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[the authorities of Travancore and later had correspondence with them. When

        Satyagraha entered the twentieth month, the temple roads, except the one on
        the eastern side, were opened to all people and the Vaikom Satyagraha ended.


        Non Cooperation Movement and Salt Satyagraha

        As decided at the Nagpur session (1920), Non Cooperation movement was

        started throughout the country.In Kerala, too, there was widespread boycott of

        foreign goods, courts and educational institutions. The Malabar Rebellion of
        1921 and the students agitation of 1922 in Travancore were events of great

        political significance during this period.


        The Salt-Satyagraha under the leadership of Gandhiji had its own repercussions
        in Kerala. Payyannur in Malabar, was the main venue of the Satyagraha in

        Kerala. Many batches of Satyagrahis from different parts of Kerala marched to

        Payyannur to take part in the Satyagraha.

        Many leaders like K. Madhavan Nair, K. Kelappan and Muhammad Abdur

        Rahiman were arrested for breaking salt-law and were sentenced to
        imprisonment. Side by side with the Salt Satyagraha, picketing of toddy shops

        and the boycott of foreign goods were also organised and large number of

        satyagrahis courted imprisonment. As there was no salt satyagraha in native
        States, freedom fighters from Cochin and Travancore went outside the States

        and broke salt law in British Indian provinces and were imprisoned. Civil

        disobedience movement came to an end with the release of Gandhiji and
        Gandhi-Irwin pact was signed on March 4, 1931.


        Temple Entry for Untouchables


        At the fifth All Kerala Political Conference held at Badagara from May 3 to 6,
        1931 under the presidency of J.M. Sengupta, many important resolutions

        including the one demanding temple entry for the so called untouchables, were
        passed. The famous Gurvayur Satyagraha (1931-32) was an off-shoot of this

        resolution. As Zamorin Raja, the hereditary trustee of Guruvayur Sreekrishna

        Temple did not agree to allow the untouchables to worship in the temple, local
        leaders decided to launch a satyagraha for achieving this end. Appeals of

        eminent people throughout India including Gandhiji, Mahakavi Rabindranath




                     FLAMES
        Independent Day Special                                                                            Page 4]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[Tagore and others to allow the untouchables into the temple had no effect on

        the adamant Zanmorin.

        A satyagraha was started under the leadership of K. Kelappan, with many

        satyagrahis being manhandled and arrested. As a last resort, Kelappan began
        ‘fast unto death’ to achieve the aim. When Kelappan’s condition became

        critical, and there were numerous appeals to save his life, Gandhiji intervened

        and persuaded him to end his fast. After that, a referendum regarding temple-
        entry of untouchables was conducted among the Hindus of Ponnani Taluk,

        where the temple was situated and a huge majority of the people voted in

        favour of throwing open the temple to them.

        Quit India Movement


        The Quit India Movement launched in August 1942 was widespread in Cochin

        and Malabar, though not so extensive in Travancore. During the Quit India
        Movement there were sensational and violent incidents in Malabar involving

        disruption of communication and attack on government offices and police
        stations. The Keezhariyur Bomb case, in which 27 persons including Dr.K.B.

        Menon, Socialist leader and Secretary of Indian Civil Liberties Union were

        charge-sheeted, was the important episode of the struggle in Malabar. Even
        underground papers like ‘Swathantra Bharatam’ were brought out during the

        struggle.


        Agitation in Travancore and Cochin

        After the Haripura session of the Indian National Congress which decided that

        separate organisations should be formed in native States for the agitation for
        responsible government, the Travancore State Congress and the Cochin State

        Prajamandal were formed.


        Both in Travancore and Cochin the autocratic regimes tried their best to
        suppress the agitation for responsible government and complete Independence.

        In Cochin State, the Government’s attitude was more liberal than that of

        Travancore government. In Travancore, Dewan Sir C.P. Ramaswami Iyer
        declared that Travancore will remain independent without joining the Indian

        Union, after the British left India. People of Travancore continued their struggle




                     FLAMES
        Independent Day Special                                                                            Page 5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[and they had to fight against ‘Independent Travancore Plan’  also. As a result of

        the agitation, at last, Dewan Ramaswami Iyer had to leave Travancore State.
        With India achieving Independence in August 1947, Travancore and Cochin

        acceded to the Indian Union.

        Struggle in Mahe


        Even after the British left India, the Portuguese and French governments were

        not prepared to leave their settlements on Indian soil. So the people in these
        settlements had to wage war against these powers. In Mahe, which was a

        French enclave on the Malabar coast, the people underwent a heroic and

        prolonged struggle till the French left their settlements in India. Freedom fight
        in Mahe forms a part of the struggle for freedom in Kerala. It may be mentioned

        that Kerala had a proud share in the Indian Independence Struggle.

























































                     FLAMES
        Independent Day Special                                                                            Page 6]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[يناطيربلا رامعتسلاا دض  رابيلم ءاملع فقوم


                                                                                  -HAFIZ MUHAMMAD YASEEN MANGAD





              ةيناطيربلا ةموكحلا دض تابلاقنلااو تاجاجتحلاا     نم اريثك رابيلم ةبرت تدهش

         اذإو . 1921  ما ع  ىف ترج ىتلا رابيلم ةروث اهرهشأو اهمهأ .دنهلا للاقتسا موي ىلإ ةليوط ةدم ةرمعتسملا
         ر ود ةلاقم لا هذ ه  يف ثحبنو .رشبلا فلاآ ةايحب تدوأ دق ةروثلا هذه نأ  فسلأل  دجن رابيلم خيرات انحفصت

                    نيملسمل ا ةاي ح  ىف ىلعملا حدقلاو ىلوطلا ديلا مهل تناك نيذلا ةملؤملا ةثداحلا هذ ه يف  رابيلم ءاملع




           ىنعم ا م   ،ةج ذاسلا ةرظنلا ببسب باجحلاو سيلاوكلا ءارو فقت  ةقيقح ىلإ مكراظنأ هّجوأ نأ ديرأ لاوأ
                    ةيس اي سلا اهتطلسل اهعضختو ةوقلاو رهقلاو حلاسلاب ىرخلأا ىلع ةلودلا للاتحا وه  ؟رامعتسلاا
                                                                                     ً
                …  هرمع ي هلعج يأ ؛ناكملا يف هرمعتسا    …  نارمعلا وأ رامعلإا بلط ةغل رامعتسلااف .ةيداصتقلااو
          ه    دابع    الل رمع تسا  … رُمعتو حلصتل ةلماعلا يديلأا نم هيلإ جاتحت امب اهدمأ يأ ،اهرّمع :ضرلأا رمعتسا
                ُ

            ﴾...ا   هي ف مُكرمْع    تْساو      ض ْ ر   ْ   لأا  نّ م مك   ُ    أ شنأ وُه﴿ :ىلاعت لوقي .اهل ا ً راّمُع و اهينكاس مهلعج يأ ،ضرلأا يف
                    ْ



             ملاس لإا راشتنا نأ كردن هتقيقحو ثحبملا اذه ةيمهأ ىلإ انراظنأ انيمر اذإف  .)دوه ةروس        –    61  ةيلآا(
            ةيام ح  عم م لاعلا يضارأ اوكلتما مهشويجو نيملسملا ءافلخ نكلو. رامعتسلااو للاتحلاا ةقيرطب  ىرجي
         نايدأ   ريغل   رضي مل ىذلا ينملأا رامعتسلاا نأ اذه نم مهفن .ةروص حضوأو هجو لم       كأب اهراجتو اهيناكس

                                        .    مهقطانمو ىرخأ نايدأ ىلع اضيأ انتاداع يه لب. ادبأ اشحاف سيل كلسمو




           انئا ملع دنع   ةبراق ملا هذه ىلع ةريثك ةلثمأ دجن اهدعبو ةروثلا هذه لبق رابيلم خيرات انضرعتسا اذإ كلذبو
           . رابيلم ي ملسم   ةايح ىف زراب رود مهل توكلاك ةاضق تناك نامزلا ميدق ذنم  .ةرقابعلا    انئارمأو لضافلأا

         نيملسمل ا نإ   كلذ ىلع ةولاع .ةيناطيربلا ةيروطاربملإا نم معدب ةلسلسلا هذه يرتوماس رابيلم كلم سسأ

           .مظع ملا  ب    صنملا اذه سيسأت ىلع مهتدعاسمو مهمعدل نيركاش ةيناطيربلا ةموكحلا ىلإ مهتلاسر اولسرأ
              نيمل سملا   عم ةديج تاقلاع نوسراميو ةنسح ةلماعم نولماعي ايناطيربلا ةاضقلا تناك اذه نم اقلاطنا
                  ة طلس سماخلا جروج كلتمي امنيح" هباتك يف  ايوك دمحم روهشملا خرؤملا لاق ىتح هجو لمكأب

              ةاضق ه ساير ب  ةملاسلاو   ةيفاعلاب هل نوعديو اذهب نولفتحي رابيلم وملسم ناك ةيناطيربلا ةيروطاربملإا
            ربج ت نود ب  ةيناطيربلا ةموكحلاب اوضر مهءاملعو رابيلم يملسم نأ قبس امم ايلج حضتا دقل "توكيلاك

                                                                                                           .  رهقتو




            لود دض ةيناطيربلا ةموكحلا عم ىلولأا ةيملاعلا برحلا ىف اوكراش نيملسملا نم ريثك كلذ ىلإ هفاضإ

         ةفلاخ تمدهنا ىتح تاونس ةدع ايناطيربو نيملسملا نيب هق       لاعلا هذه  رمتسا دق .للب لاو للم نودب ىرخأ




                     FLAMES
        Independent Day Special                                                                            Page 7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[فشكني..... اهماسقنا يف تطلسو ملاعلا يملسم ةفلاخ دهعم ىلع ايناطيرب ىلوتساو ايكرت ىف نيملسملا

         ةفلاخ ىلإو ةيناطيربلا ةموكحلا ىلإ ةلاسر ولسرأ رابيلم يملسم نأ ةداجلا ةيعوضوملا ةساردلا ءوض ىف

         ةيواستم ةفقو فقو عم نيبزحلا لاك ءامد كفس نودب برحلا هذه ءاهنإ يف ةبغر رامعتس           لاا اذه لبق ايكرت
           زهتنا .اهماسقناو ايكرت ةفلاخ ىلع ايناطيرب حاجن دعب بقع ىلع اسأر روملأا تبلقنا  نكل .نيقيرفلا نم
                  دض نوملسملا دشتحا ىتح ةيعاجرتسا ةليحب هصرفلا هذه  يدناغ امتاهمو ينطولا بعشلا بزح

            ناك امم لاوحلأا بلقت لب .ءودهو نوكسب ةفلاخلا ةكرح ءاسؤرو ينطولا بعشلا بزح عم ايناطيرب               لا
          رشبلا فلاآ فتح يقلو ىلتقلا ثثج مكارت عقو ىتح ةفلاخلا كيرحت ءاسؤرو ىنطولا بعشلا بزح عقوتي

             ةرو ثلا هذه  نم اوجن .ىودج نود تعجر مهتلاواحم ثيحب رمجلاب بلقتي ينطولا بعشلا بزح تاب.
               باتكلا فيلأت دعب  ةمامإ لاو ةسائر نودب رابيلم لاوط نارينلا  تلعتشاو . روهمجلا فطاوع ةراثإب

         يف باتكلا اذه ةيناطيربلا ةموكحلا تلعج. رايلسم ىتوكيرب سردملاو ملاعلا ملقب "نيدلا تامهم" روهشملا
          نأ ملسملا ىلع يغبني" .هاواتف ىف   رايلسم يتوكيرب لاق .اهراداصإو اهتءارق تم ّ رح يتلا ءارمحلا ةمئاقلا

        للاقتسلاو  هيلإ نيملسملا ةنامأ ىّدؤُي يذلا ةماملإا بصن  رسيتيل ةدشو ةوقب ةيناطيربلا ةموكحلا دض اوفقي
          ةيروطاربملإا لبق ايكرت ىف رمدت ىتلا  ةفلاخلا بصن يه ةيساسلأا هتياغ نأ انه نم مهفن  " اضيأ اندلاب

          نجنك مهمظعأو مهرهشأ نمو . نانف نم نيروهشملا  ءاملعلا نم ريثك ىوتفلا           هذه ركنأ نكلو .ةيناطيربلا
          دبعو رابيلم ىف  يلمرلا ماملإاب ىلحتملا يرغناتت مايلسم مايتكو رابيلم ىف رجح نباب بقلملا رايلسم اوباب

              هذه أر قن ."ةفلاخلا مسا نع ةفلاقلا كحم" مساب "نيدلا تامهم" باتك دض مهاواتف نونلعي .رايلسم الل
         مل كلذ نوضع يف . نينس ةئام ثلاث ابيرقت دنهلا نومكحي ةيناطيربلا  ةموكحلا نيملسملا اوهبتنا" يواتفلا

          ىلع ايوق انمأ ملاسلإا نيد ىف لخدي نمل نودعاسي مه لب انطابو ارهاظ نيدلا عئارش ماكحأ هتموكح فني
              هذه دض ةروثلا بنتجي نأو رخفو خ      ومشب مهءارو وفقي نأ نيملسملا ىلع يغبني كلذلو .مهنايدأ لصأ

                                    .  ةرتفلا هذه ىف ءارملأا رباكأو ءاملعلا لضافأ ةبراقم وه اذه "ةينملأا ةموكحلا

            ىفر ابيلم   ءاملع ةيعمج سيسأتب مهءاطخأ رايلسم يتك دمحأ لغنابو لّكرو ديسلا ححص ةروثلا هذه دعب

               ةف لاخ مادهنا ذنم ةروثلا هذ ه لبق ينطولا بعشلا بزح ىلإ امضنا ناصخشلا ناذه ثيحب           1921 ماع
         ةموكحل ا دض   تاروث بانتجاب مهاواتف تردصأ رابيلم ءاملع ةيعمج نأ  روملأا هذه ثدح ام دعبو  .ايكرت

         اريث ك  نأ ي نادلا عم يصاقلا هب فرتعا امم.  كورف رمتؤم ىف ينطولا بعشلا بزح مامضناو  ةيناطيربلا
          اهطس و  ىفو .ةل يوط ة رتف اهلبقو ةملؤملا ةروثلا هذه دعب ةبر اقملا هذه  اوبراق  لاريك ةيلاو يف ءاملعلا نم

           ،ايكر ت  ىف ت مدهأ ىتلا ةفلاخلا بصنل ةيناطيربلا ةموكحلا دض ءارملأاو ءاملعلا نم ةليلق ةمذرش لماع
         علاطا   ىندأ هل   نم ىل ع  ىفخي لا امم ... .ادبأ اهللاقتسا لاو ايناطيربلا نم دنهلا دادرتساب تسيل مهتياغ  لب

               دض    مادصلا بنجتل نيملسملا اوحصن رابيلم ءاملع نأ  سمشلا حوضوك حضتا دقل رابيلم خير           ات ىف
                       م    لسو ه يلع الل ىلص يبنلا نامز ذنم ملاسلإا ملع امك ةديج ةلماعم مهعم اولماعتيو ايناطيربلا


















                     FLAMES
        Independent Day Special                                                                            Page 8]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[ಜಪ್ರನಿೀಯರ ಶಸ್ಥತ ರಸತ ರಗಳನ್ನು  ಒದಗಿಸಿಕಟ್ಟ್  ಬೀಸರು ಸೇನೆಗ್ರ ಹೊಸ

        ಚೇತನವನ್ನು  ತುಾಂಬ್ರದರು. ಜೈ಺ಿಾಂದ್, ಚಲೀ ಧಿಲ್ಲಿ -ಎಾಂಬ ಶಿೀರ

        ಘೀಷಣೆಗಳನ್ನು  ಬಳಕ್ಕಗ್ರ ತಂದರು. ಯುದಧ ಧಿಾಂದಲ್ಿ ದ್ ಭೇರಾವ

        ಸ್ಥರ್ನಧಿಾಂದಳೂ ಭಾರತದ ಸ್ಥವ ತಂತೆ ೂ  ಸ್ಥರ್ೂ ಶಿಲ್ಿ ವಾಂದ್ದ ಘೀಷ್ಟಸಿ,

        ಚಳವ಴ಿಯನ್ನು  ಸಮರದ ತಳಹಧಿಯ ಮೇಲೆ ಱೂಪಿಸಿ, ತೀವೆ ಗೊ಴ಿಸಿದರು.

        ಮುಖ್ೂ  ಸೇನ್ಯನಿಪತೂ ವನ್ನು  ತಾವೇ ವ಺ಿಸಿಕಾಂಡು, ದಂಡೆತತ  ಹೊೀಗಿ ಬ್ರೆ ಠಿಷ್

        ಹೈನೂ ದ ಮೇಲೆ ಬ್ರದ್ದದ , ಅವರನ್ನು  ಅವರ ನೆಲ್ಗಳನ್ನು  ರ್ವ ಾಂಸ
        ಮ್ರಡತಡಗಿದರು. ಚಳವ಴ಿಯನ್ನು  ಕೆ ಮಬದಧ ವಾಗಿರೂ ದಕ್ಷತ್ರಿಾಂದಳೂ

        ನಡೆಸುವ ಉದ್ದ ೀಶಧಿಾಂದ ಅವರು ಆeóÁದ್ ಺ಿಾಂದ್ ತಾತಾೆ ಲ್ಲಕ ಸಕಾರದ


        ಯೂಲ್ ಕಾಂದೆ ವನ್ನು  ಸಿಾಂಗಪುರಧಿಾಂದ ರಂಘೂನಿಗ್ರ ವಗಾರಿಸಿದರು.

        ಇಾಂಢಿಯನ್ ನ್ಯೂ ಷನಲ್ ಆಮ್ಮಾ- ಈ ಹೆಸಱಿನ ಪೆ ಸಿದಧ  ಹೈನೂ ವನ್ನು  ಕಠಿ್ ದವರು

        ಸುಭಾಸ್ ಚಂದ ೆ  ಬೀಸ್. ಕಠಿ್ ದ ಸಂದರ್ಾ ಗಮನ್ಯಹಾವಾದ್ದದ್ದ. ಮೊದಲ್

        ಮಹಾಯುದಧ ವಾದ ಮೇಲೆ ಭಾರತೀಯ ರಾಷ್ಟ್ ರೀಯ ಚಳವ಴ಿಯನ್ನು  ದೂರ

        ಪ್ರೆ ಚೂ ದಳೂಿ  ಹರಡಲು ಮೊಟ್ ಮೊದಲ್ನೆಯದಾಗಿ ಪೆ ಯತು  ಮ್ರಢಿದವರು

        ರಾಶ್ ಬ್ರಹಾಱಿ ಬೀಸ್. ಈ ಪೆ ಯತು ದ ಫಲ್ವಾಗಿ ಜಪ್ರನಿನಲ್ಲಿ  ಭಾರತೀಯ

        ಸ್ಥವ ತಂತೆ ೂ  ಮಂಡಲ್ಲ ಸ್ಥಾ ಪಿತವಾರಿತು. ಜಪ್ರನಿೀಯರ ಸಹಾಯ,
        ಸಹಕರಧಿಾಂದ ಕ್ಕಲ್ಸವನ್ನು  ಆರಂಮಿಸಿದ ರಾಶ್ ಬ್ರಹಾಱಿ ಬೀಸ್ ಎರಡನೆಯ

        ಮಹಾಯುದಧ  ಪ್ರೆ ರಂರ್ವಾಗುವವರೆಗ್ರ ಅಹೊೀರಾತೆ  ದ್ದಢಿದರು. 1944ನೆಯ

        ಸ್ಥಪ್್ ಾಂಬರ ು ಲ್ಲ ಿ  ಇಟಲ್ಲ ಸೀತು ಶರಣಾದ್ದದ್ದ ಅಜಾದ್ ಺ಿಾಂದ್ ಚಳವ಴ಿಗ್ರ ಭಾಱಿ

        ಪ್ಟ್ಟ್  ಬ್ರದದ ಾಂತಾರಿತು. ಅಮ್ಮಱಿಕ ಪ್ಸಿಫ್ರಕ್ ಸ್ಥಗರದಲ್ಲಿ  ತನು  ನೆಲೆಗಳನ್ನು

        ಮತ್ತ  ಪಡೆದ್ದಕಾಂಡದದ ಱಿಾಂದ ಜಪ್ರನ್ ಹೆಚ್ಚಿ ನ ಗಮನವನ್ನು  ತನು  ನಗರ

        ರಕ್ಷಣೆಯ ಕಡೆ ಹಱಿಸಭೇಕರಿತು. ತತಪ ಱಿಣಾಮವಾಗಿ ಅಜಾದ್ ಺ಿಾಂದ್ ಹೈನೂ ಕ್ಕೆ
        ನಿಱಿೀಕ್ಷಿ ಸಿದಷ್ಟ್  ಪೆ ಮ್ರಣದಲ್ಲಿ  ನೆರವನ್ನು  ಜಪ್ರನ್ ಕಡಲಾರದ್ ಹೊೀರಿತು.


        ಇಾಂಡೀ-ಬಮಾ ಗಢಿಯಲ್ಲಿ  ಅಜಾದ್ ಺ಿಾಂದ್ ಹೈನೂ  ನಡೆಸಿದ ಹೊೀರಾಟ
        ಸ್ಥಥಾಕವಾಗಲ್ಲಲ್ಿ . ಹೈನೂ  ಶಿೀರಾವೇಶಧಿಾಂದ ಯುದಧ

        ಮ್ರಢಿದಱೂ ಇಾಂಫಾಲ್ ಮತುತ  ಕ಺ಿಮ ಆಕೆ ಮಣಗಳಲ್ಲಿ

        ಸೀತುಹೊೀರಿತು. ಮತಿಪುರವನ್ನು  ರಕ್ಷಿ ಸುವುದಕೆ ಗಿ ಬ್ರೆ ಟನ್ ಶಕ್ಷತ ಮ್ಮೀಱಿ

        ಹೊೀರಾಢಿತು. ಅದರ ಶಸ್ಥತ ರಸತ ರಗಳು ಉತತ ಮ ದರ್ಜಾಯವಾಗಿದದ ವು. ಸವ ಲ್ಪ ಕಲ್ದ

        ಮೇಲೆ ಗಢಿಯ ಸಮರಗಳಲ್ಲಿ  ಬ್ರೆ ಠಿಷ್ ಯುದಧ  ಯಂತೆ ಗಳ ಬಳಕ್ಕಯನ್ನು




                     FLAMES
        Independent Day Special                                                                           Page 12]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[FLAMES
        Independent Day Special                                                                           Page 13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[(ಐಕನ್) ಆಗಿ ಉ಴ಿಧಿದದ  ಗಾಂನಿಯವರಾಂಧಿಗ್ರ ಸಂಬಂರ್ ಹೊಾಂಧಿತು.

        ಆಟಮನ್ ಕಲ್ಲೀಫತ್`ನ ಸಂರಕ್ಷಣೆಗ್ರ ಹೊೀರಾಡಲು 1920 ರಲ್ಲಿ  ಗಿಲಾಫತ್

        ಚಳವ಴ಿಯಾಂಧಿಗ್ರ ಅವರು ಯೈತೆ  ಮ್ರಢಿಕಾಂಡರು ಭಾರತೀಯರು


        ಆಾಂದೀಲ್ನಕೆ ಗಿ ‘ನ್ಯಗಱಿಕ ಅಸಹಕರ’ ಚಳುವ಴ಿ ಅಥವಾ ಸತಾೂ ಗೆ ಹವನ್ನು

        ಬಳಸುವ ಹಕ್ಕೆ ಗಳನ್ನು  ಹೊಾಂಧಿದದ ರು. 1923 ರಲ್ಲಿ , ಚೌಱಿ ಚೌರಾದಲ್ಲಿ ನ

        (ನಿಯಮ ತಪಿಪ ದ ಸತಾೂ ಗೆ ಺ಿಗಳ ಺ಿಾಂಸ್ಥರಿಾಂದ) ಪೊಲ್ಲೀಸ್ ಅನಿಕಱಿಗಳ ಸ್ಥಶಿನ

        ನಂತರ ಗಾಂನಿಯವರು ಆಾಂದೀಲ್ನವನ್ನು  ಅಮ್ರನತುತ ಗೊ಴ಿಸಿದರು.

        ಪೆ ತರ್ಟನೆಯಲ್ಲಿ , ಇದನ್ನು  ಒಪಪ ದ್ ಪೆ ತರ್ಟನೆಯಾಗಿ, ಚ್ಚತತ ರಂಜನ್ ದಾಸ್,
        ಅನಿು  ಬೆಸ್ಥಾಂಟ್ ಮತುತ  ಮೊೀತಲಾಲ್ ನೆಹಱೂ ಮೊದಲಾದ ಹಲ್ವಾರು

        ನ್ಯಯಕರು ಸವ ರಾಜ್ ಪಕ್ಷವನ್ನು  ಸ್ಥಾ ಪಿಸಲು ರಾಝಿೀನ್ಯಮ್ಮ ನಿೀಢಿದರು.


        ಗಿಲಾಫತ್ ಚಳುವ಴ಿ ಶಿಫಲ್ವಾರಿತು ಮತುತ  ಕಾಂಗ್ರೆ ಸ್ ಶಿರ್ಜನೆಯಾರಿತು.

        ಸದಾಾರ್ ವಲ್ಿ ರ್ಭಾರಿ ಪಟೇಲ್, ಪಂಢಿತ್ ಜವಾಹರಲಾಲ್ ನೆಹರು, ಡಾ.

        ರಾಜಾಂದೆ  ಪೆ ಸ್ಥದ್, ಖಾನ್ ಮೊಹಮೆ ದ್ ಅಬಾಾ ಸ್ ಖಾನ್, ಖಾನ್ ಅಬುದ ಲ್

        ಘಫಾರ್ ಖಾನ್, ಚಕೆ ವತಾ ರಾಜಗೊೀಪ್ರಲಾಚಾಱಿ, ಡಾ. ಅನ್ನಗೆ ಹ

        ನ್ಯರಾಯಣ್ ಸಿನ್ಯಾ , ಜಯಪೆ ಕಶ್ ನ್ಯರಾಯಣ್, ಝಿೀವತ್ ರಾಮ್ ಕೃಪ್ರಲಾನಿ,

        ಮತುತ  ಮೌಲಾನ್ಯ ಅಬುಲ್ ಕಲಾಮ್ ಆಜಾದ್. ಮೊದಲಾದವರು
        ಗಾಂನಿಯವರ ಜನಪಿೆ ಯತ್ ಮತುತ  ಅವರ ಸತಾೂ ಗೆ ಹ ಎಾಂಬ ಹೊಸ

        ಚಳುವ಴ಿಯ ಅಥವ ಕೆ ಾಂತಯ ತಂತೆ ಕ್ಕೆ  ಮ್ಮಚ್ಚಿ  ಗನಿಝಿೀಯವಱಿಗ್ರ


        ಬೆಾಂಬಲ್ನಿೀಢಿದರು. ಇದಲ್ಿ ದ್ ಚಾಲ್ಲತ ಯಲ್ಲಿ ದದ  ರಾಷ್ಟ್ ರೀಯತ್ಯ ಪಱಿಣಾಮ,
        ಮತುತ  ಜಾತ ಮಿನು ತ್ಗಳ ಶಿರೀದ, ಅಸಪ ೃಶೂ ತ್ ನಿವಾರಣೆ, ಬಡತನ

        ನಿಯೂಾಲ್ನೆಗ್ರ ಒತುತ , ಮತುತ  ಧಾಮ್ಮಾಕ ಮತುತ  ಜನ್ಯಾಂಗಿೀಯ ಶಿಭಾಗಗಳನ್ನು

        ನಿಯೂಾಲ್ನೆ ಮ್ರಡುವ ಪಕ್ಷದ ಪೆ ಯತು ಗಳು, ಕಾಂಗ್ರೆ ಸ್` ಪೆ ಬಲ್ವಾದ ಮತುತ

        ಶಕ್ಷತ ಯುತವಾದ ಸಂಗಟನೆಯಾಗಿ ಮ್ರಪಾಠಿ್ ತು. ಅದರ ಸದಸೂ ರು

        ಪೆ ಧಾನವಾಗಿ ಺ಿಾಂದೂಗಳಾಗಿದದ ಱೂ, ಅದ್ದ ಇತರ ರ್ಮಾಗಳು, ಆರ್ಥಾಕ

        ವಗಾಗಳು ಮತುತ  ಜನ್ಯಾಂಗಿೀಯ ಮತುತ  ಭಾಷ್ಯ ಗುಾಂಪುಗಳ ಸದಸೂ ರನ್ನು

        ಹೊಾಂಧಿತುತ .

        ಜವಾಹರಲಾಲ್ ನೆಹಱೂ ಅವರ ಅರ್ೂ ಕ್ಷತವ ದಲ್ಲಿ  ಕಾಂಗ್ರೆ ಸ್ 1929 ಲಾಹೊೀರ್

        ಅನಿವೇಶನ, ಫೂಣಾ ಸವ ರಾಜ್ ಅನ್ನು  (ಫೂಣಾ ಸ್ಥವ ತಂತೆ ೂ ವನ್ನು ) ಪಕ್ಷದ

        ಗುಱಿಯಾಗಿ ಘೀಷ್ಟಸಲಾರಿತು, 26 ಜನವಱಿ 1930 ರಂದ್ದ "ಫೂಣಾ ಸವ ರಾಜ್

        ಧಿವಸ್" (ಸ್ಥವ ತಂತೆ ೂ  ಧಿನ) ಎಾಂದ್ದ ಘೀಷ್ಟಸಿತು. ಶಿಪಯಾಾಸವಾಂದರೆ ಅದೇ



                     FLAMES
        Independent Day Special                                                                           Page 14]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[ವಷಾ, ಅದಕ್ಷೆ ಾಂತ ಮೊದಲು ಗಾಂನಿಯವರು ಸವ ದೇಷಿ ಡಮ್ಮನಿಯನ್

        ಆಡ಴ಿತಕೆ ಗಿ ಭೇಢಿಕ್ಕ ಇಠಿ್ ್ ದದ ರು. ಅವರು ಮ್ರಢಿದ ಆ ಭೇಢಿಕ್ಕಯನ್ನು

        ಶಿರೀನಿಸಿ ಡಮ್ಮನಿಯನ್ ಆಡ಴ಿತವಲ್ಿ , ಫೂಣಾ ಸ್ಥವ ತಂತೆ ೂ ವನ್ನು

        ಕೀಱಿದದ ಕೆ ಗಿ ಷಿೆ ೀನಿವಾಸ್ ಐಯೂ ಾಂಗರ್ ಅವರನ್ನು  ಪಕ್ಷಧಿಾಂದ

        ಹೊರಹಾಕಲಾಗಿತುತ .. ಆದರೆ ನಂತರ ನೆಹಱೂ ಅವರ ಒತಾತ ಯಧಿಾಂದ "ಫೂಣಾ

        ಸ್ಥವ ತಂತೆ ೂ " ವನ್ನು  ಪಡೆಯುವುದ್ದ- ಕಾಂಗೆ ಸಿಿ ನ ಗುಱಿಯಾಗಿ

        ಘೀಷ್ಟಸಲಾರಿತು.


        ಸುಭಾಷ್ ಚಂದೆ  ಬೀಸ್ 1938-39ರ ಅವನಿಯಲ್ಲಿ  ಕಾಂಗ್ರೆ ಸ್`ನ ಅರ್ೂ ಕ್ಷರಾಗಿ

        ಕಯಾನಿವಾ಺ಿಸಿದರು. ಸ್ಥವ ತಂತೆ ದ ಮೊದಲ್ ಹಂತವಾಗಿ ಪ್ರೆ ಾಂತಗಳಲ್ಲಿ
        ಚುನ್ಯರಿತ ಸಕಾರ ರಚನೆಗ್ರ ಅವಕಶಶಿರುವ “1935 ರ ಭಾರತ ಸಕಾರ


        ಕರಿದ್”ಯನ್ನು  ಅಾಂಗಿೀಕಱಿಸಿದ ನಂತರ, ಪ್ರೆ ಾಂತೀಯ ಚುನ್ಯವಣೆಗಳು 1936-37


        ರ ಚ಴ಿಗಲ್ದಲ್ಲಿ  ಹನ್ು ಾಂದ್ದ ಪ್ರೆ ಾಂತಗಳಲ್ಲಿ :ನದ್ದವು. ಅವು ಮದಾೆ ಸ್,

        ಕಾಂಧಿೆ ೀಯ ಪ್ರೆ ಾಂತಗಳು (ಈಗಿನ ಉತತ ರಪೆ ದೇಶ ಮತುತ  ಇತರ ಭಾಗಗಳು),
        ಬ್ರಹಾರ, ಒಱಿಸ್ಥಿ , ಯುಪೈಟ್ರ್ಡ ಪ್ರೆ ಾಂತೂ ಗಳು, ಬಾಾಂಬೆ ಪ್ೆ ಸಿಡೆನಿಿ , ಅಸ್ಥಿ ಾಂ,


        ಬಂಗಳ, ಪಂಜಾಬ್ ಮತುತ  ಸಿಾಂಧ್. ಈ ಚುನ್ಯವಣೆಗಳಲ್ಲಿ  ಸಪ ನಿಾಸಿದ ನಂತರ,

        ಭಾರತೀಯ ರಾಷ್ಟ್ ರೀಯ ಕಾಂಗ್ರೆ ಸ್ ಬಂಗಳ, “ಪಂಜಾಬ್ ಮತುತ  ಸಿಾಂಧ್”

        ಹೊರತುಪಢಿಸಿ ಎಾಂಟ್ಟ ಪೆ ದೇಶಗಳಲ್ಲಿ  ಕಾಂಗೆ ಸ್ ಅನಿಕರವನ್ನು  ಪಡೆರಿತು.
        ಅಗಿಲ್ ಭಾರತ ಮುಸಿಿ ಾಂ ಲ್ಲೀಗ್ ಯಾವುದೇ ಪ್ರೆ ಾಂತೂ ದಲ್ಲಿ  ಸಕಾರವನ್ನು

        ಱೂಪಿಸಲು ಶಿಫಲ್ವಾರಿತು. ಎರಡ಩ೇ ಮಹಾಯುದಧ  ಆರಂರ್ ವಾರಿತು.

        ಅದರಲ್ಲಿ  ಭಾರತ ಸೇಱಿದ್ ಎಾಂದ್ದ ಶೈಸ್ಥೆ ಯ್ ಲಾರ್ಡಾ ಲ್ಲನಿಿ ತಿ  ಅವರು

        ಘೀಷಿಸಿದರು. ಅವರ ಘೀಷಣೆಯನ್ನು  ಪೆ ತರ್ಠಿಸಿ, ಅಕ್ ೀಬರ್ 1939 ಮತುತ

        ನವಾಂಬರ್ 1939 ರಲ್ಲಿ  ಕಾಂಗ್ರೆ ಸ್ ಮಂತೆ ಗಳು ರಾಝಿೀನ್ಯಮ್ಮ ನಿೀಢಿದರು.

        ಭಾರತೀಯ ಜನರ ಪಿೆ ನಿನಿಗಳನ್ನು  ಸಂಪಕ್ಷಾಸದೇ ಎರಡ಩ೇ ಜಾಗತಕ

        ಯುದಧ ದಲ್ಲಿ  ಭಾರತವು ಯುದಧ ದಲ್ಲಿ  ತಡಗಿದ್ ಎಾಂಬ ಸಕಾರದ ನಿಲುವನ್ನು

        ಕಾಂಗ್ರೆ ಸ್ ಶಿರೀನಿಸಿತು.

        1939 ಮತುತ  1939 ರಲ್ಲಿ  ಚುನ್ಯರಿತ ಅರ್ೂ ಕ್ಷ ಸುಭಾಷ್ ಚಂದೆ  ಬೀಸ್ ಅವರು

        ಕಯಾಕಱಿ ಸಮ್ಮತಯ ಆಯ್ಕೆ ಗ್ರ ಅಸಮ್ರಧಾನಪಟ್ಟ್  ಕಾಂಗ್ರೆ ಸ್` ಪಕ್ಷಕ್ಕೆ

        ರಾಝಿೀನ್ಯಮ್ಮ ನಿೀಢಿದರು. ಈ ಪಕ್ಷವು ಭಾರತೀಯ ರಾಜಕರಣದ ಏಕೈಕ

        ಪೆ ತನಿನಿಯಾಗಿರಲ್ಲಲ್ಿ , ಇತರ ಪಕ್ಷಗಳು ಅಗಿಲ್ ಭಾರತೀಯ ಺ಿಾಂದೂ





                     FLAMES
        Independent Day Special                                                                           Page 15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[ഖിലാഫത്ത് പ്രസ്ഥാനം


                                                                                -HAFIZ MUHAMMAD NAWFAL





                  അവിഭക്തഇന്ത്യയിൽ പ്രത്യയകിച്ച് മുസ്ലിങ്ങൾക്കിടയി

        ൽ 1919 മുയൽ 1926 വരെ ഉണ്ടായ ഒെു രാൻ

        ഇസ്ലാമിക ൊഷ്്പ്ടീയ മുത്േറ്റമായിെുേു ഖിലാഫത്ത്


        പ്രസ്ഥാനം. മുസ്ലിങ്ങളുരട ആത് ാള ത്നയൃയവമായ യുർക്കി

        ഖിലാഫത്തിരനയിൊയ പ്രിട്ടന്രെ നീക്കത്തിരനയിരെ ഒെു

        പ്രയിത്ഷ്ധം എേ നിലയിലാണ് ഖിലാഫത്ത് പ്രസ്ഥാനം

        ആെംഭം കുെിക്കരെട്ടയ് രിേീട് അയ് സവായപ്ന്ത്യ

        സമെങ്ങളുരട ഭാ ം എേ വിശാല ലക്ഷ്യത്ലക്ക്

        രെിവർത്തനം രെയ്യരെടുകയുണ്ടായി.മൗലാനാ മുഹമ്മദ്

        അലി ഖിലാഫത്ത് പ്രസ്ഥാനത്തിന്രെ ഇന്ത്യയിരല പ്രധാന

        ത്നയാക്കളിൽ ഒൊളായിെുേു.ത്കെളത്തിലും ഖിലാഫത്ത്

        പ്രസ്ഥാനം വലിയ ത്യായിൽ െലനങ്ങൾ

        ഉണ്ടാക്കിയിെുേു.മലരാർ കലാരത്തിൽ ത്നയൃയവം

        നൽകിയവെിൽ പ്രമുഖനായ ഖിലാഫത്ത്

        ത്നയാവായിെുേുവാെിയൻ കുേത്ത് കുഞ്ഞഹമ്മദ്

        ഹാജി. ഏെനാട് കലാരത്തിൽ ത്രാൊടിയ


        ത്നയാവായിെുേു. ഖിലാഫത്ത്

        പ്രസ്ഥാനത്തിൻരെമുൻനിെയിൽ നിേ്

        പ്രിട്ടീഷ്ുകാർരക്കയിരെയും, മലരാെിരല ഹഹന്ദവ

        ജന്മി പ്രിട്ടീഷ്് അനുകൂല മുസ്ിം പ്രമാണിമാർരക്കയിരെയും

        ത്രാൊടിയ ആലി മുസ്ിയാെുരട സന്ത്യ സഹൊെിയും,

        ശിഷ്യനുമായിെുേു അത്േഹം.75,000ത്ത്താളം വെുേ ഒെു

        വലിയ ത്സനരയ കൂരട നിർത്തിയാണ് യന്രെ

        സമാന്ത്െഭെണകൂടം സ്ഥാരിച്ചയ്.





                     FLAMES
        Independent Day Special                                                                           Page 23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[ഇന്ത്യ ഇേ് ത്നെിടുേ ഏറ്റവും വലിയ ൊഷ്്പ്ടീയ വിരത്തിരന

        അയ് ഖിലാഫത്ത് പ്രത്ക്ഷ്ാഭവുമായി കൂട്ടിരക്കട്ടുേു

        എേയാണു.


        ഖിലാഫത്ത് പ്രത്ക്ഷ്ാഭത്തിന്രെ നൂൊം വർഷ്ത്തിൽ ആനന്ദ്

        അവിരട നിേ് 2019രല നത്െപ്ന്ദ ത്മാദിയുരട വിജയത്തിത്ലക്ക്

        ഒെു വെ വെയ്ക്കുകയാണു. ഇന്ത്യയുരട ഭാവിൊഷ്്പ്ടീയ


        രെിണയികളിൽ ഖിലാഫത്ത് പ്രസ്ഥാനം സവാധീനം

        രെലുത്തിരയേും  ാഩൎധിയും ത്കാണ്‍പ് സും ഖിലാഫത്ത്

        പ്രസ്ഥാനരത്ത വെത്വറ്റയ് ത്ദശീയ പ്രസ്ഥാനത്തിരല ഏറ്റവും


        വലിയ അരദ്ധമായിെുേുരവേുമാണു ആനന്ദ് എഴുയുേയ്.

        അയായയ്, അത്േഹം രത്ൊക്ഷ്മായി രെഞ്ഞു വയ്ക്കുേയ്


        ഇന്ത്യയിരല മയൊഷ്്പ്ടീയത്തിന്രെ ത്വെുകൾ ഖിലാഫത്ത്

        പ്രത്ക്ഷ്ാഭത്തിത്ലക്കാണ്ടു കിടക്കുേുരവേും അയ് അേ്

        യിെിച്ചെിയാൻ  ാഩൎധിത്ക്കാ ത്കാണ്‍പ് സിത്നാ കഴിഞ്ഞില്ല


        എേുമാണു.


        ഒോമയായി ആനന്ദ് ത്ലഖനത്തിന്രെ യുടക്കത്തിൽ

        എഴുയുേയു ത്രാരല 1919ൽ യുർക്കി സവയം ഒെു

        മയനിെത്രക്ഷ് െിരബ്ലിക്കായി മാെുകയും ഖിലാഫത്ത്

        ആശയം നിലനിൽക്കുകയുമായിെുേില്ല. 1919ൽ ഒോം


        ത്ലാകയുദ്ധം ത്യാരറ്റങ്കിലും യുർക്കിയിൽ അത്ൊഴും

        സുൽത്താനുണ്ട്.



        സുൽത്താത്നറ്റ് അത്രാളിഷ്് രെയ്യരെടുേയ് 1922ലാണു,

        സവായപ്ന്ത്യ യുദ്ധം മുസ്തഫാ കമാൽ വിജയിച്ചയിനു ത്ശഷ്ം.

        അവസാന സുൽത്താൻ രമഹ്മദ് ആൊമൻ യുർക്കി വിടുേയ്

        1922 നവമ്പെിലാണു. രിത്േയും െണ്ടു വർഷ്ം കഴിഞ്ഞിട്ടാണു


        മുസ്തഫാ കമാൽ ഖിലാഫത്ത് അത്രാളിഷ്് രെയ്യുേയ്.




                     FLAMES
        Independent Day Special                                                                           Page 24]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[ഏയാണ്ട് അത്യ സമയത്ത്താരട ഇന്ത്യയിലും ഖിലാഫത്ത്

        പ്രസ്ഥാനം രകട്ടടങ്ങിയിെുേു.





        െണ്ടാമയായി ഖിലാഫത്തിന്രെ (caliphate) ശെിരയറ്റുകൾ

        മാപ്യമാണു ആനന്ദിന്രെ ത്ലഖനവിഷ്യരമങ്കിൽ അത്േഹം

        ഖിലാഫത്തിരനയിരെ ഉേയിക്കുേ രല വാദങ്ങളും


        പ്രസക്തമാണു

        രത്ക്ഷ് പ്രശ്നം, ഖിലാഫത്ത് പ്രത്ക്ഷ്ാഭരത്ത

        ഉരഭൂഖണ്ഡത്തിരല വിഭജനത്തിന്ത്െയും


        മയൊഷ്്പ്ടീയത്തിന്ത്െയും ഉെവയായി കാണുേിടത്താണു.

        ഈ വാദത്തിനാകരട്ട യാരയാെു രയളിവും ആനന്ദ്

        ത്ലഖനത്തിൽ നിെത്തുേുമില്ല. ഖിലാഫത്ത് എേു രെയുേയ്

        മുസ്ിങ്ങൾ ഒെു ൊജയമാരണേും അവെുരട ഭെണാധികാെി


        ഖലീഫയാരണേുമാണു.





        ‘രയാള്ളായിെത്തി ഇെുരയുകളിൽ മുസ്ിം ലീ ിന്രെ

        മയൊഷ്്പ്ടവാദത്തിനു സമാന്ത്െമായി ഹിന്ദുയീപ്വവാദികൾ


        മുത്ോട്ടു വച്ചയും സാമാനയജനയ അവ ണിച്ചയുമായ

        ഫാസിസ്റ്് ത്സ്റ്റ്റിന്രെ വികൃയെൂരം മുൻവായിലിലൂരട കടേു

        വേിെിക്കുേു.’


        ഇയ് വസ്തുയാവിെുദ്ധമാണു. മയൊഷ്്പ്ടം എേ


        ഡിമാൻഡിത്ലക്ക് ലീ ് വെുേയ് 1930കളിലാണു. (Muhammad

        Iqbal’s speech at League Conference in 1930). ലാത്ഹാർ രെസലൂഷ്ൻ

        വെുേയ് 1940ലാണു. അയിനും മുൻര് സവർക്കർ ഇവിരട


        ദവിൊഷ്്പ്ട സിദ്ധാന്ത്ം രെഞ്ഞിട്ടുണ്ട്. അല്ലാരയ ആനന്ദ്

        ഒഴുക്കൻ മട്ടിൽ രെയുേ ത്രാരല ലീ ിന്രെ



                     FLAMES
        Independent Day Special                                                                           Page 25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[ಹೆಚಾಿ ಗತಡಗಿತು. ಬಂಗಳದಲ್ಲಿ  ಫ್ೆ ಾಂಚರ ವಾೂ ಪ್ರರ

        ವ಺ಿವಾಟ್ಟಗ಴ೂಹೆಚಿ ತಡಗಿದವು. ನವಾಬನ ಭಾಱಿೀ ಶಸ್ಥತ ರಸತ ರಗಳನ್ನು


        ನಿವಾ಺ಿಸಲು ತಮೆ  ಹೈನಿಕರನ್ನು  ಅವರು ಸ್ಥಲ್ವಾಗಿ ನಿೀಢಿದರು.

        ಸಿರಾಜುದ್ದದ ಲ್ನಿಗ್ರ ಎರಡು ಕಡೆರಿಾಂದ ಸಂಕಟ ಉಾಂಟಾರಿತು. ಬ್ರೆ ಠಿಷರ ಈಸ್್

        ಇಾಂಢಿಯಾ ಕಂಪನಿ ಒಾಂದ್ಡೆಯಾದರೆ, ಅವನ ಪ಼ಷಿಿ ಮದ ಗಢಿಯಲ್ಲಿ  ಅಫಘಾನ

        ಅಹಮದ್ ಶಹಾ ಬಾದ ಲ್ಲಯ ಹೈನೂ


        ಮುನ್ನು ಗಿ ತಡಗಿತುತ . ಅಬಾದ ಲ್ಲಯ

        ಹೈನೂ ವು೧೭೫೬ರಲ್ಲಿ  ದ್ಹಲ್ಲ ವಶಪಢಿಸಿಕಾಂಡು ಳೂಠಿ ಮ್ರಢಿತುತ .

        ಸಿರಾಜುದ್ದದ ಲ್ನ್ನ ತನು  ಹೈನೂ ದ ದಡಡ  ಭಾಗವನ್ನು  ತನು  ಪಿೆ ಯ ಮ್ಮತೆ  ಮತುತ
        ಬೆಾಂಬಲ್ಲಗ ಪಟಾು ದ ಧಿವಾಣ ರಾಮನ್ಯರಾಯಣನಮುಖಂಡತವ ದಲ್ಲಿ

        ಅಬಾದ ಲ್ಲಯ ಹೈನವ ನ್ನು  ಎದ್ದಱಿಸಲು ಕಳು಺ಿಸಿದನ್ನ.ಇಷ್ ರ ಮಧ್ಯೂ  ಸಿರಾಜುದ್ದದ ಲ್

        ನ ಮುಷಿಾದಾಬಾಧಿನಆಸ್ಥಾ ನದಲ್ಿ ರೂಕರಸ್ಥಾ ನಗಳುಶುರುವಾಗಿದದ ವು. ಆತ

        ಅಷ್್ ೀನ್ನ ಜನಪಿೆ ಯ ದರೆಯಾಗಿರಲ್ಲಲ್ಿ . ತನು  ಅಜಜ ನ ನಂತರ ಪಟ್ ಕ್ಕೆ

        ಬಂದಾಗ ೨೩ರ ಹರೆಯದಲ್ಲಿ ದದ  ಅವನ್ನ ತನು  ಷಿೀಘೆ ಕೀಪದ ಸವ ಭಾವಧಿಾಂದ

        ಬಹು ಭೇಗ ಶತುೆ ಗಳನ್ನು  ಮ್ರಢಿಕಳುು ತತ ದದ .ಅವರಲಿ ಬಾ ಳು , ಅತ

        ಷಿೆ ೀಮಂತ಴ೂ, ಗಂಡಾಾಂತರಕಱಿರೂ ಆದ ಘಸೇಠಿ ಭೇಗಂ ಎಾಂಬ ಅವನ

        ಚ್ಚಕೆ ಮೆ . ಭೇರಬಾ  ಸೀದರ ಸಂಬಂನಿ ದರೆಯಾಗಭೇಕ್ಕ ಎಾಂದ್ದ ಅವಳ

        ಇಚ್ಚೆ ಯಾಗಿತುತ . ಇವಳಲ್ಿ ದ್ ಕಲ್ಕತಾತ  ಮುತತ ಗ್ರರಿಾಂದ ತಾಂದರೆಗೊಳಗದ
        ಶಹಾ ಮತುತ  ಸೇನ್ಯ ಮುಖ್ೂ ಸ್ಥಾ ನಧಿಾಂದ ಪದಚುೂ ತನ್ಯದ ಮ್ಮೀರ್  ಜಾಫರ್


        ಇವಱೂ ಪೆ ಬಲ್ ಶತುೆ ಗಳಾಗಿದದ ರು.

        ರಾಜೂ ದ ನ್ಯಯಕತವ ದ ಬದಲಾವಣೆ ತಮೆ  ಺ಿತಾಸಕ್ಷತ ಗ್ರ ಅವಶೂ ಕ ಎಾಂದ್ದ

        ಕಂಪನಿಯವರು ಮೊದಳೇ ನಿರ್ಾಱಿಸಿಯಾಗಿತುತ . ೧೭೫೨ರಷ್ಟ್  ಮೊದಳೇ

        ರಾಬಟ್ಾ ಓಮ್ಮಾ ಎಾಂಬಾತನ್ನ ರಾಬಟ್ಾ ಕ್ಕಿ ೈವನಿಗ್ರ ಬರೆದ ಪತೆ ದಲ್ಲಿ

        ಸಿರಾಜುದ್ದದ ಲ್ನ ಅಜಜ  ಅಲ್ಲವಧಿಾ ಖಾನನ್ನು  ಪದ್ದೂ ತಗೊ಴ಿಸುವುದ್ದ ಕಂಪನಿಯ
        ಅಮಿಷೃಧಿಧ ಗ್ರ ಅಗತೂ  ಎಾಂದ್ದ ಬರೆಧಿದದ ನ್ನ. ೧೭೫೬ರಲ್ಲಿ  ಅಲ್ಲವಧಿಾ ಖಾನನ

        ಅಕಲ್ ಮರಣದ ನಂತರ ಅವನ ಉತತ ರಾನಿಕಱಿಯಾಗಿ ಸಿರಾಜುದ್ದದ ಲ್ನ

        ಹೆಸಱಿತುತ . ಅವನನ್ನು  ಅಲ್ಲವದ್ ಾಖಾನನ್ನ ದತುತ  ತ್ಗ್ರದ್ದಕಾಂಢಿದದ ನ್ನ. ಈ

        ಬದಲಾವಣೆಯ ವೇಳೆಗ್ರ ನಡೆದ ಕ್ಕಲ್ ಬೆಳವತಿಗ್ರಗಳು ಸ್ಥಕಷ್ಟ್  ಶಿವಾದಕ್ಕೆ

        ಕರಣವಾಗಿ , ಬ್ರೆ ಠಿಷರು ಈ ಅವಕಶವನ್ನು ಉಪಯೀಗಿಸಿಕಾಂಡು






                     FLAMES
        Independent Day Special                                                                           Page 34]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[]]></page></pages></Search>